<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Tutorial | OpenAphid]]></title>
  <link href="http://openaphid.github.com/blog/categories/tutorial/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://openaphid.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-05-03T22:18:13+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://openaphid.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aphid Mobile]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[openaphid@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tutorial: Developer Mode of OpenAphid]]></title>
    <link href="http://openaphid.github.com/blog/2012/05/02/develop-mode-of-openaphid/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-02T14:52:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://openaphid.github.com/blog/2012/05/02/develop-mode-of-openaphid</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><code>Developer Mode</code> is a feature to speed up developing games with OpenAphid. The behavior of OpenAphid changes if the developer mode is turned on.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>How to Enable Developer Mode?</h2>

<p>Open your project with Xcode and locate the following lines in <code>OAAppDelegate.m</code>:</p>

<p>``` objective-c
[self.viewController.glViewController configBundleName:@"game.bundle"</p>

<pre><code>                                           baseURL:[NSURL URLWithString:@"http://129.158.217.36:18080"]
                                       developMode:YES];
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Setting the value of the <code>developMode</code> parameter to <code>YES</code> enables the developer mode of OpenAphid;</p></li>
<li><p>An HTTP server should be used to host the content inside the bundle folder specified by <code>configBundleName</code>. The value for the <code>baseURL</code> parameter should be set to the server address too. A ruby based tiny HTTP server is included in our boilerplate project, please refer to the <code>web_server.rb</code> and <code>start_dev_server.sh</code> files for more details;</p></li>
<li><p>The application should be built and re-deployed to devices with the new settings.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>And for the <a href="https://github.com/openaphid/Boilerplate-iOS">Boilerplate-iOS</a> project, <code>UIApplicationExitsOnSuspend</code> is <code>YES</code> in its info.plist file; which makes the app terminate automatically when the Home button is pressed.</p>

<h2>Changes in Developer Mode</h2>

<p>The main benefit of using developer mode is that it makes the game development speedy like developing for web:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>JavaScript files are fetched from the HTTP server. If you want to see the result of your changes in the game script, you only need to re-open the app;</p></li>
<li><p>Graphics resources are fetched remotely too. For example, a texture can be created by using <code>new aphid.g2d.Texture2D("player.png")</code>; the <code>player.png</code> file is fetched via <code>http://129.158.217.36:18080/player.png</code> in developer mode. OpenAphid Runtime also prints a log about it as following:</p></li>
</ul>


<p><code>
INFO 05/02/12,13:41:32: (developer mode) loading data 'player.png' from remote: http://129.158.217.36:18080/player.png
</code></p>

<ul>
<li>Internal warning and error messages are displayed as on-screen notifications besides logging in device console. Warning messages are in blue background color and errors are in red color. The screenshot below shows a notification about a syntax error in a JavaScript file:</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/developer-mode-error-notification.png" title="Notification" alt="Error Notification" /></p>

<ul>
<li><p>Messages produced by <code>console.warn</code> and <code>console.error</code> are also displayed as notifications;</p></li>
<li><p>Write access to read-only attributes of OpenAphid objects throws exception in developer mode.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>With the developer mode of OpenAphid, the typical development process is as follows:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Developer edits the JavaScript file with game logics and updates graphic files inside the bundle folder;</p></li>
<li><p>Presses the home button and enters the app again to see the result of the changes;</p></li>
<li><p>Following the on-screen notifications and console logs to diagnose mistakes in JavaScript files.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Hope you like the developer mode of OpenAphid. We'll improve it constantly to make game development easier. Please feel free to contact us if you have any suggestions.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
